Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Roger Shimomura papers
1965-1990
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Shimomura, Roger
2.6 linear feet
The papers of painter, printmaker, performance artist, and teacher Roger Shimomura measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1965 to 1990. Found within the papers are biographical materials, correspondence, writings, notes, printed material, one scrapbook, and photographs.
Provenance
Roger Shimomura donated his papers in 1990, as part of the Archives of American Art's Northwest Asian-American project in Seattle.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Roger Shimomura (b. 1939) is a Japanese-American painter, printmaker, performance artist, and teacher who has worked primarily in Kansas since 1969.
Roger Shimomura was born in 1939 in Seattle, Washington. He was a third generation Japanese-American and received his B.A. in Graphic Design from the University of Washington in 1961, and a M.F.A. in Painting from Syracuse University in 1969. Shimomura spent two childhood years in one of 10 concentration camps for Japanese-Americans during WWII, and later served as an officer in the United States Army from 1962 to 1965. He was active in the Japanese-American redress movement in the 1970s. Since the 1970s, Shimomura's work has combined American popular imagery with the Japanese ukiyo-e tradition.
He has had over 125 solo exhibitions of paintings and prints, as well as presented his experimental theater pieces at such venues as the Franklin Furnace, New York City, Walker Art Center, Minneapolis, and The Smithsonian Institution, Washington, DC. Shimomura has been a visiting artist and lectured on his work at more than 200 universities, art schools, and museums across the country. Shimomura began teaching at the University of Kansas' Department of Art in 1969 and worked there until his retirement in 2004. At that time he started the Shimomura Faculty Research Support Fund, an endowment to foster faculty research in the Department of Art. Throughout his career, Shimomura has had numerous exhibitions and experimental theater pieces on a national level. In 1999, the Seattle Urban League designated a scholarship in his name that has been awarded annually to a Seattle resident pursuing a career in art. In 2002, the College Art Association presented him with the ??Artist Award for Most Distinguished Body of Work,?? for his 4 year, 12-museum national tour of the painting exhibition, ??An American Diary.?? Shimomura continues to live and work in Kansas.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of painter, printmaker, performance artist, and teacher Roger Shimomura measure 2.6 linear feet and date from 1965 to 1990. Found within the papers are biographical materials, correspondence, writings, notes, printed material, one scrapbook, and photographs.
Biographical materials include a photograph of Shimomura and a resume. The bulk of the papers consist of correspondence files about exhibitions, grants, performances, lectures, and the Japanese-American redress movement. Correspondence is with friends, colleagues, galleries, and with universities and colleges. Correspondents include Frank Chin, Akiko Day, Jonathan R. T. Hughes, and Wayne Miller. Writings and notes include Shimomura's artist's statement, scripts to four plays, and one folder of miscellaneous notes. The papers also include clippings, exhibition announcements, catalogs and miscellaneous printed material. A scrapbook contains clippings of articles that document Shimomura's career. Photographs are of artwork by other artists.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1989-1990 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1969-1990 (Boxes 1-3; 2.3 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, 1984, 1987-1989 (Box 3; 5 folders)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1975-1990 (Box 4; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 5: Scrapbook, 1975-1989 (Box 4; 1 folder)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1970s (Box 4; 1 folder)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Art--Study and teaching--Kansas--Lawrence; Asian American artists; Japanese Americans; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945; Japanese American painting; Painters--Kansas--Lawrence; Painting, Modern--20th century--United States; Performance art--United States; Performance artists--Kansas--Lawrence; Printmakers--Kansas--Lawrence
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Scrapbooks; Scripts(documents)
Names:
Chin, Frank, 1940-; Day, Akiko; Hughes, Jonathan R. T.; Miller, Wayne
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1989-1990, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Biographical material includes a photograph of Shimomura and a detailed resume.
  - Biographical Material, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1969-1990, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-3; 2.3 linear feet)
  Correspondence is primarily with friends and colleagues including Frank Chin, Akiko Day, Jonathan R. T. Hughes, and Wayne Miller. Topics include the Japanese-American redress movement, lectures, performances, and exhibitions. A large portion of the correspondence is with galleries and concerns exhibitions and business matters. Other types of correspondence include grant applications and files about the exhibition "A Kansas Collection" (1986-1987) and the Seattle Transit Project (1986-1989).
  - General Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General Correspondence, 1969-1990, (18 folders) (Box 1, Folder 3-20)
  - Akiko Day, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Frank Chin, 1978-1989, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
  - John Hughes, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Wayne Miller, 1978-1990 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous Galleries, 1965-August 1983, (17 folders) (Box 1, Folder 28-44)
  - Miscellaneous Galleries, September 1983-1987, (5 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - "A Kansas Collection" Exhibition, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Alberta College of Art, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Center on Contemporary Art, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cleveland State University, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Denver Art Museum, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dobrick Gallery, 1976-1984 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Downtown Seattle Transit Project, 1986-1989, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - East Illinois University, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Elaine Horwitch Gallery, 1976-1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Franell Gallery, Tokyo, 1975-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Gallery Heian, Kyoto, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Greg Kucera Gallery, 1984-1990, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - Iowa State University, 1988-1990 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Kansas City Art Institute, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Kiku Gallery, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Locus, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Loyola University, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Memorial Union Gallery, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Michael Wyman Gallery, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Morgan Art Gallery, 1976-1988, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Polly Friedlander Gallery, 1973-1982, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
  - Pyramid Galleries, Ltd., 1975-1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Sebastian-Moore Gallery, 1977-1986, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
  - University of California-Davis, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - University of Kansas, 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - University of North Dakota, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Woodside-Braseth Galleries, 1980-1984 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Individual Sales and Inquiries, 1973-1989, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 38-40)
  - Grant Applications, 1970-1975, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 41-43)
  - Grant Applications, 1976-1989, (11 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-11)
- Writings and Notes, 1984, 1987-1989, Series 3:; (Box 3; 5 folders)
  Writings include Shimomura's artist's statement, scripts to "The Funky Odori", "Trans-Siberian Excerpts" (1987), "Seven Kabuki Plays Project" (1987), and "California Sushi" (1989). A single folder of notes includes an illustrated list and a list of participators in the 1984 Asian-American History Theatre Summer Workshop.
  - Artist's Statement, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "The Funky Odori" Script, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Trans-Siberian Excerpts" Script, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Seven Kabuki Plays" Project Script, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "California Sushi" Script, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Miscellaneous, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Printed Material, 1975-1990, Series 5:; (Box 4; 0.2 linear feet)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements, catalogs, and miscellaneous printed material.
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated, 1975-1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1984-1990 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, 1980-1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, 1986-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Clippings, undated, 1975-1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous, undated, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Scrapbook, 1975-1989, Series 6:; (Box 4; 1 folder)
  The scrapbook series includes a compilation of photocopied articles documenting Shimomura's career from the mid 1970s until the late 1980s.
  - Scrapbook, 1975-1989 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Photographs, circa 1970s, Series 7:; (Box 4; 1 folder)
  Photographs are of works of art by other artists.
  - Works of Art by Others, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 8)